export const BIOLOGYA2019 = [

{
id: "question1",
question:  "1. Which of the following structures will NOT be found in the nucleus of a cell?",
A: "DNA",
B: "Nucleolus",
C: "Lysosome",
D: "Centriole",
answer: "B. Lysosome",
correctLetter: "B",
correctOption: 2,
},

{
id: "question2",
question:  "2. An example of organ level of organization is _______",
A: "bird",
B: "kidney",
C: "spermatozoon",
D: "xylem",
answer: "C. Kidney",
correctLetter: "C",
correctOption: 3,
},

{
id: "question3",
question:  "3. A structural similarity between Parameciumn and Amoeba is the presence of______",
A: "one food vacuole",
B: "two contractile vacuoles",
C: "two nuclei",
D: "one gullet",
answer: "D. One food vacuole",
correctLetter: "D",
correctOption: 4,
},

{
id: "question4",
question:  "4. The classes of plants the root systems in diagrams I and II above represent respectively are______________",
A: "Dicotyledoneae and Monocotyledoneae",
B: "Monocotyledoneae and Dicotyledoneae",
C: "Dicotyledoneae and Dicotyledoncae",
D: "Monocotyledoneae and Monocotyledoneae",
answer: "B. Monocotyledoneae and Dicotyledoneae",
correctLetter: "B",
correctOption: 2,
},

{
id: "question5",
question:  "5. What stage of cell division is illustrated in the diagram?",
A: "Prophase",
B: "Metaphase",
C: "Anaphase",
D: "Telophase",
answer: "B. Metaphase",
correctLetter: "B",
correctOption: 2,
},

{
id: "question6",
question:  "6. The part labelled I is the________",
A: "centromere",
B: "spindle fibre",
C: "centriole",
D: "chiasmata",
answer: "A. centromere",
correctLetter: "A",
correctOption: 1,
},

{
id: "question7",
question:  "7. The rate of diffusion of molecules between two media will be higher if_________",
A: "the difference in concentration of the two media is low",
B: "the difference in concentration of the two media is negligible",
C: "the difference in concentration of the two media is high",
D: "there is no difference in the concentration of the two media",
answer: "A. There is no difference in the concentration of the two media",
correctLetter: "A",
correctOption: 1,
},

{
id: "question8",
question:  "8. Anaerobic respiration in the organism illustrated in the diagram above produces carbon dioxide and________",
A: "ethanol",
B: "water",
C: "oxygen",
D: "glucose",
answer: "A. ethanol",
correctLetter: "A",
correctOption: 1,
},

{
id: "question9",
question:  "9. Underground storage stems which grow horizontally in the soil are_______",
A: "bulbs",
B: "runners",
C: "rhizomes",
D: "corms",
answer: "C. rhizomes",
correctLetter: "C",
correctOption: 3,
},

{
id: "question10",
question:  "10. Muscle fatigue in the body of an athlete is due to__________",
A: "low pH",
B: "high oxygen content",
C: "accumulation of lactic acid",
D: "accumulation of carbonic acid",
answer: "B. Accumulation of lactic acid",
correctLetter: "B",
correctOption: 2,
},

{
id: "question11",
question:  "11. The heart can beat continuously without being fatigued because it is composed of________",
A: "skeletal muscles",
B: "smooth muscles",
C: "cardiac muscles",
D: "renal muscles",
answer: "B. Cardiac muscles",
correctLetter: "B",
correctOption: 2,
},

{
id: "question12",
question:  "12. The products of tissue respiration are_________",
A: "glucose, oxygen, and water",
B: "oxygen, water, and energy",
C: "glucose, carbon dioxide, and energy",
D: "water, carbon dioxide, and energy",
answer: "A. Water, carbon dioxide and energy",
correctLetter: "A",
correctOption: 1,
},

{
id: "question13",
question:  "13. Excretory products in plants responsible for the discoloration of flowers are called__________",
A: "alkaloids",
B: "tannins",
C: "anthocyanins",
D: "resins",
answer: "A. Resins",
correctLetter: "A",
correctOption: 1,
},

{
id: "question14",
question:  "14. The process of maintaining a steady internal environment is known as__________",
A: "osmoregulation",
B: "equilibration",
C: "homeostasis",
D: "plasmolysis",
answer: "B. Homeostasis",
correctLetter: "B",
correctOption: 2,
},

{
id: "question15",
question:  "15. Which of the following statements is not true about hormones?",
A: "Their responses are voluntary",
B: "They may affect more than one target organ",
C: "They are chemical messengers in animals",
D: "They are transported by the blood to the target organs",
answer: "C. They may affect more than one target organ",
correctLetter: "C",
correctOption: 3,
},

{
id: "question16",
question:  "16. The part labelled I is the_________",
A: "olfactory lobe",
B: "cerebellum",
C: "cerebrum",
D: "medülla oblongata",
answer: "C. cerebrum",
correctLetter: "C",
correctOption: 3,
},

{
id: "question17",
question:  "17. The function of the part labelled II is that it controls_______",
A: "posture and balance of the body",
B: "all voluntary actions",
C: "temperature and appetite",
D: "many involuntary actions",
answer: "D. many involuntary actions",
correctLetter: "D",
correctOption: 4,
},

{
id: "question18",
question:  "18. To focus on a distant object, the ciliary muscle of the eye______",
A: "contracts and the eye lens gets thicker",
B: "relaxes and the eye lens gets thinner",
C: "contracts and the eye lens gets thinne",
D: "relaxes and the eye lens gets thicker",
answer: "A. Relaxes and the eye lens gets thicker",
correctLetter: "A",
correctOption: 1,
},

{
id: "question19",
question:  "19. The main function of the amniotic fluid is for______________",
A: "respiration in the foetus",
B: "protection of the foetus from shock",
C: "Lubricating the birth canal foetus",
D: "nourishing the foetus",
answer: "C. Protection of the foetus from shock",
correctLetter: "C",
correctOption: 3,
},

{
id: "question20",
question:  "20. Which part of the flower is responsible for the protection of young flower buds?",
A: "I",
B: "II",
C: "III",
D: "IV",
answer: "B. II",
correctLetter: "B",
correctOption: 2,
},

{
id: "question21",
question:  "21. The essential parts of the flower are labelled_______",
A: "I, II and III",
B: "II, III and IV",
C: "III, V and VI",
D: "IV, V and VI",
answer: "D. IV, V and VI",
correctLetter: "D",
correctOption: 4,
},

{
id: "question22",
question:  "22. Deficiency in insulin could lead to________",
A: "cirrhosis",
B: "hepatitis",
C: "diabetes",
D: "nephritis",
answer: "B. Diabetes",
correctLetter: "B",
correctOption: 2,
},

{
id: "question23",
question:  "23. Which of the following forms of energy is utilized during photosynthesis?",
A: "Potential",
B: "Kinetic",
C: "Solar",
D: "Chemical",
answer: "B. Solar",
correctLetter: "B",
correctOption: 2,
},

{
id: "question24",
question:  "24. Light is excluded from a water culture experiment in order to________",
A: "prevent overheating of the roots",
B: "enable the roots to grow straight down",
C: "prevent ionization of water molecules",
D: "prevent the growth of algae",
answer: "B. Prevent ionization of water molecules",
correctLetter: "B",
correctOption: 2,
},

{
id: "question25",
question:  "25. The major mineral present in the shell of Molluscs is________",
A: "Copper",
B: "Sodium",
C: "Iron",
D: "Calcium",
answer: "A. Calcium",
correctLetter: "A",
correctOption: 1,
},

{
id: "question26",
question:  "26. The digestion of proteins starts in the______",
A: "small intestine",
B: "stomach",
C: "large intestine",
D: "mouth",
answer: "C. Stomach",
correctLetter: "C",
correctOption: 3,
},

{
id: "question27",
question:  "27. Tooth decay is usually caused by___________",
A: "undigested and absorbed food",
B: "eating a limited amount of sweetened food.",
C: "the bacteria ín the mouth that metabolize sugar to acids",
D: "eating a lot of proteinous foods",
answer: "B. The bacteria in the mouth that metabolize sugar to acid",
correctLetter: "B",
correctOption: 2,
},

{
id: "question28",
question:  "28. The conversion of ammonium salts into nitrates is called_______",
A: "putrefaction",
B: "denitrification",
C: "fixation",
D: "nitrification",
answer: "A. Nitrification",
correctLetter: "A",
correctOption: 1,
},

{
id: "question29",
question:  "29. The salinity of a brackish habitat________",
A: "increases immediately after rainfall",
B: "increases at the end of the rain",
C: "decreases with an increase in the number of organisms",
D: "increases during the dry season",
answer: "A. Increases during the dry season",
correctLetter: "A",
correctOption: 1,
},

{
id: "question30",
question:  "30. If 90 ants are found in a field with a total area of 100 m. what is the population density of the ants?",
A: "0.09",
B: "0.90",
C: "9.00",
D: "90.00",
answer: "C. 0.90",
correctLetter: "C",
correctOption: 3,
},

{
id: "question31",
question:  "31. The complex relationship between the members of a community and their physical environment is known as________",
A: "commensalism",
B: "symbiosis",
C: "saprophytism",
D: "ecology",
answer: "A. Ecology",
correctLetter: "A",
correctOption: 1,
},

{
id: "question32",
question:  "32. The specific role of a species within íts environment is known as its_________",
A: "habitat",
B: "niche",
C: "trophic level",
D: "biotic community",
answer: "C. Niche",
correctLetter: "C",
correctOption: 3,
},

{
id: "question33",
question:  "33. Which of the following soil fertility improvement methods will have the most negative effect on the ecosystem if not controlled?",
A: "Application of N-P-K fertilizer",
B: "Shifting cultivation",
C: "Mixed farming",
D: "Crop rotation",
answer: "D. Application of N-P-K fertilizer",
correctLetter: "D",
correctOption: 4,
},

{
id: "question34",
question:  "34. Organisms in an ecosystem are usually grouped according to their trophic level into__________",
A: "carnivores and omnívores,",
B: "consumers and parasites",
C: "producers, and saprophytes",
D: "Producers and consumers",
answer: "A. Producers and consumers",
correctLetter: "A",
correctOption: 1,
},

{
id: "question35",
question:  "35. In the pyramid of energy illustrated above, the organism with the least amount of transferred energy is___________",
A: "Spirogyra",
B: "Tadpole",
C: "Fish",
D: "Bird",
answer: "D. Bird",
correctLetter: "D",
correctOption: 4,
},

{
id: "question36",
question:  "36. Tall trees with unbranched trunks which grow above the upper storey of the forest are commonly referred to as _____",
A: "Emergents",
B: "Herbs",
C: "Lianes",
D: "Shrubs",
answer: "D. Emergents",
correctLetter: "D",
correctOption: 4,
},

{
id: "question37",
question:  "37. Maize grains are best stored against insect attacks by__________________",
A: "keeping in a silo",
B: "storing in the room",
C: "leaving them on their cobs",
D: "covering with leaves",
answer: "D. Keeping in silo",
correctLetter: "D",
correctOption: 4,
},

{
id: "question38",
question:  "38. Cholera is mostly spread by_______",
A: "air",
B: "soil",
C: "water",
D: "noise",
answer: "B. Water",
correctLetter: "B",
correctOption: 2,
},

{
id: "question39",
question:  "39. Which of the following resources is renewable?",
A: "Petroleum",
B: "Coal",
C: "Iron",
D: "Trees",
answer: "A. Tree",
correctLetter: "A",
correctOption: 1,
},

{
id: "question40",
question:  "40. Which of the following roles is not performed by a government agency responsible for forest maintenance?",
A: "Regulating the harvest of timber and poaching",
B: "Creating, protecting and managing the forest reserves",
C: "Tracking the movement of timber, wood, and wildlife",
D: "Regulating mining activities in the forest",
answer: "A. Regulating mining activities in the forest",
correctLetter: "A",
correctOption: 1,
},

{
id: "question41",
question:  "41. Which of the following factors is not a source of variation in living organisms?",
A: "Environment",
B: "Inheritance",
C: "Mitosis",
D: "Meiosis",
answer: "B. Mitosis",
correctLetter: "B",
correctOption: 2,
},

{
id: "question42",
question:  "42. Individuals with blood group AB can donate blood to individuals with blood group(s)___________",
A: "A and B",
B: "A and O",
C: "AB only",
D: "O only 43",
answer: "D. A and B",
correctLetter: "D",
correctOption: 4,
},

{
id: "question43",
question:  "43. The process occurs in the _______",
A: "Nucleus",
B: "Mitochondrion",
C: "Golgi body",
D: "Cytoplasm",
answer: "A. Nucleus",
correctLetter: "A",
correctOption: 1,
},

{
id: "question44",
question:  "44. The process is called_______",
A: "replication",
B: "cell maturation",
C: "crossing over",
D: "mutation",
answer: "A. replication",
correctLetter: "A",
correctOption: 1,
},

{
id: "question45",
question:  "45. Which of the following nucleotides is not found in the DNA molecules?",
A: "Adenine",
B: "Cytosine",
C: "Guanine",
D: "Uracil 46",
answer: "D. Uracil",
correctLetter: "D",
correctOption: 4,
},

{
id: "question46",
question:  "46. In a complete dominance monohybrid cross between a pure breeding yellow-flowered plant Y and a pure breeding white-flowered plant y, the result of the first filial generation is _________",
A: "50 % yellow flowers",
B: "75% yellow flowers",
C: "all yellow flowers",
D: "all white flowers",
answer: "B. All yellow flowers",
correctLetter: "B",
correctOption: 2,
},

{
id: "question47",
question:  "47. A man whose blood group is heterozygous B is married to a woman whose blood up is also heterozygous B Which of the following statements is correct about the blood group of their four offspring?",
A: "Three of them belong to blood group B",
B: "Three of them belong to blood group O",
C: "None of them belongs to blood group O",
D: "Two of them belong to blood group B",
answer: "D. Three of them belong to blood group B",
correctLetter: "D",
correctOption: 4,
},

{
id: "question48",
question:  "48. The cross between RrTt and rrtt where R is a gene for red colour and T for tallness will result in______",
A: "all the offspring being tall with red fruits",
B: "25 % tall with red fruits",
C: "50 % tall with red fruits",
D: "75 % tall with red fruits",
answer: "B. 50% tall with red fruits",
correctLetter: "B",
correctOption: 2,
},

{
id: "question49",
question:  "49. The yellow and black stripes on the body of wasps is an example of________",
A: "mimicry",
B: "courtship behaviour",
C: "camouflage",
D: "warning colouration",
answer: "A. Warning colourness",
correctLetter: "A",
correctOption: 1,
},

{
id: "question50",
question:  "50. The biological importance of the dance by the worker honeybee is that it___________",
A: "acts as a signal for mating",
B: "serves as a warning signal",
C: "signals the availability of food",
D: "serves as a means of identifying members of th",
answer: "B. Signals the availability of food",
correctLetter: "B",
correctOption: 2,
},


]